[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net survey to
share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host akshay manchali my guest
today is mike del balto and we'll be
talking about feature stores
mike is the co-founder of techton where
he is focused on building next
generation data infrastructure for
operational machine learning before
tecton mike was the pm lead for uber
michelangelo machine learning platform
prior to uber he was a product manager
at google where he managed the core ml
systems that power their search ads
business
mike welcome to the show hey thank you
for having me awesome so let's start
with some context for the rest of the
episode can you briefly describe what a
feature store is yeah so a feature store
we think of it kind of like a data
platform
to support the data flows that are
needed
in a production machine learning
application so
machine learning applications
have two components to them of course
there's models and
there are data pipelines that feed the
right input signals to those models so
the models can use that data to make a
prediction and there's a lot of
operational challenges around both the
models and the data
you know we need to organize these
models and data pipelines we need to
productionize and serve them and monitor
them and so those signals those data
pipelines that are part of a machine
learning application those those uh data
inputs to a model are called features
and so the term feature store
refers to a piece of infrastructure that
organizes the data pipelines for machine
learning application and provides some
of the implementation for
productionizing these data pipelines and
using them in uh you know in a
customer-facing ml application say for a
live recommendation service or a a live
fraud detection service let's take that
example of say a live recommendation
service and can you explain just the
terminology of what makes a feature what
is a model those components can you
explain that in the context of say that
live recommendation service great so if
we if we're an e-commerce company and we
want to show
a recommendation to the user who's
browsing the website we want to
recommend an item for them to that they
may also want to buy for example we may
have just intuitively a variety of
signals a variety of things that that
influence what we think this user might
be interested in right maybe this user
previously was looking at you know
women's fashion so we know that maybe
they're probably interested in items
related to women's fashion but maybe
also today in the session that they were
on their website today they were
they were clicking around a lot
specifically in uh pants and so maybe we
have that kind of gives us another clue
that maybe they're looking for women's
pants
and
they also may have just typed in into a
search box
capris or something like that and so
that's that's another signal that's
actually a very like high intent user
signal from there
which is kind of something that's
delivered in real time it's not about
looking at the history of the user so
point is like all of all of these
signals that all this information we can
collect about a user for uh for a given
kind of decision we want to make is
we we can all use this to kind of feed
into a decision-making process and we
can do that intuitively as humans you
know it's kind of obvious like how to
think about this stuff
but it's not always clear how to develop
a software system to
generate that recommendation and an
accurate recommendation
and not just to develop such a system
but to also like rely your business on
that you know if you have you have a
website that's making money how do you
make this a reliable software
application how do you have reliable
predictions that are tuned to the
high quality predictions that
lead to more sales for example
and so high quality recommendations so
the parts there are
you know we need
a machine learning model which is
something that is
the system that takes these data inputs
in and makes the decision of hey this is
the item we should recommend in this
instance
and that machine learning model is trend
so it learns from a variety of
historical examples so it we would like
learn this machine learning model from
a variety of historical examples of
impressions that the user has seen from
previous recommendations and and
and also data about whether they clicked
those those recommendations or not and
that's called the training data set and
that's what
a machine learning model is built on it
looks at all these historical examples
we run those examples through
what's called a training algorithm and
that outputs basically a decision making
system that
can act on it's almost like a
transformation that acts on
the
input some input data and can output
which
item we want to recommend and as you
build that model you can configure the
the training algorithm to optimize for
different things and so
we may
configure it to
optimize for
i likely like the highest click-through
rate like we want to
recommend the object maybe the piece of
the the
like the fashion article clothing that
is the most likely thing that we think
someone will click on and that will
correlate
quite well to us increasing our revenue
if we have higher quality
recommendations
so that model
depends on having these signals that we
just thought about and we just talked
about intuitively right like what does
this person typically search for and
what did they type in the search box
right now
the model needs that data and a very
structured format in a very in and a
very specific format for it to be able
to act on it and for it to be able to
interpret that data and and use for its
decision making process
and the
data and so there's special data
pipelines that are set up
that one has to build while they're
building a machine learning application
to both generate that historical
training data set for to uh for a model
to be trained on
and also to generate the latest versions
of all of these signals when a model is
making predictions so when we're
building a model we need to
look through a process our logs data to
come up with here's all the times
someone saw a recommendation before this
is what we knew about them
these are the signals that we knew at
that at that point in time in the past
so this is kind of like historical
feature values
at this time at this time in the past
someone had searched had just searched
for men's pants someone had just
searched for a hat something like that
and then this is what we recommended and
then this is
whether or not
that user clicked on the recommendation
or not and we compile all of that and
that becomes the training data set and
it's a it's a real data process there's
a lot of people put a lot of work into
into the data process for compiling that
data set
and that's what we you know you often
hear ml people say like you know 90 of
doing machine learning is data cleaning
data preparation
that's what that work is to prepare that
data set
and then when you want to use that model
and and now we're getting into the
deployment we've built them we've built
the prototype at least
we've come up with the model we want we
want to productionize that there's a
similar set of data pipelines that are
used to deliver those data signals to
the model at production time and those
have to be
real-time pipelines that represent the
current state of those features for the
current session the current user their
current context does that make sense
yeah the second part of that is what you
mean by operationalizing your machine
learning model so can you walk through
what the general challenges are in terms
of taking this recommendation system
that i may have built with
training data test data with a set of
features and then operationalizing that
in actual production system so what is
that what are the challenges there yeah
i think the the biggest challenges are
are actually that there's just not one
way to do this there's we're kind of
we're kind of uh
you know it's kind of it's it's kind of
a new thing for a lot of companies to
that are even software companies they've
been doing they've been building
software and depending on it for that
being their product for a long time but
adopting machine learning
is uh as kind of a new challenge for
them and so
that brings with it uh some different
development processes there's different
there there's different
ways to productionize that i'll talk
about but there's also different ways to
monitor and maintain these systems
there's different things that one has to
track to allow them to identify issues
to allow them to debug these systems and
address kind of like outages as well so
so when someone thinks about like what
is unique about
or what are unique challenges of
building and deploying ml systems
compared to typical software
there's a really interesting kind of
difference here is that we're not just
compiling a single binary and deploying
a binary we're compiling something that
that has a very
specific external dependencies on
data pipelines on data resources that
are always being updated so when people
talk about like i'm deploying my machine
learning system it's your machine
learning system is both the model
artifact but it's also these these data
dependencies that need to be maintained
and they are always changing they're
very dynamic they
you know that's that's data that's
always being processed
and
you know
deploying a
simple machine learning system
is not as big of a challenge as uh
deploying some of the more complicated
or sophisticated ml systems that are
used for higher for more like higher
value ml use cases
so
they're very important to that business
so think about like a pricing system for
a
insurance company or think about like
surge pricing for uber or the
estimated time of arrival for uber or
even an estimated click-through rate for
google where google's trying to you know
make sure they show you ads that you
would click on right they don't want to
show your ads you're not going to click
on
and
a lot of these use cases have they're
very valuable and they and and uh
high accuracy is very important for
these use cases and that motivates
finding as many ways as possible to
bring in additional
signal to make a model more accurate so
the more
fresh signals the more the the
more d context we can get the better
kind of information and data we can get
about what's going on right now that
that's kind of obvious like it's
intuitive for us as humans
that we can feed into a model
more likely the better that that model
will be and that will lead to some
business impact so so in practice what
happens is
these ml applications that
are quite meaningful that are uh that
have real economic impact like some of
the ones i just mentioned
there is a really complicated whole nest
of of data pipelines different services
that are built to support these uh to
process all the different types of data
that the that the business is seeing
that the business has and
and translate that data extract the
signal aggregate that data you know mix
and match this data and and extract the
signal and convert it to a format that's
consumable by the model and deliver in
real time to a model so some of these
signals are computed in real time some
of them are you know batch signals stuff
like that like we just talked about some
of them are based on streaming
infrastructure on kafka and
some of the challenges some of the
biggest challenges for these teams are
just keeping all of these tools up and
running and if you're a data
scientist you're not going to be an
expert in all of these different
technologies and so that's why like a
lot of these more sophisticated ml
more valuable ml use cases they have
huge teams of engineers supporting them
and that makes that makes ml kind of
like uh not accessible like meaningful
ml not accessible for teams that cannot
staff up giant engineering teams yeah so
you do have like data engineers who can
actually bring
the idea that might be
conceived by a data scientist into
reality by building these pipelines and
if i'm hearing you right you're you're
saying the quality of signal also
depends on various sources and various
characteristics that are in different
places you mentioned kafka so you could
have streaming data you could have a
data warehouse so how is all of these
things how are all these things usually
connected is there some example that you
can
share which drives the point about the
complexity involved in building these
data pipelines from different sources to
actually operationalize a machine
learning model yeah totally well so
there's there's kind of the like how are
they usually collect connected for
you know
a lot of a lot of companies that are
practically getting started with this
today and then there's how are these
things connected in the most efficient
way or in the way that companies that
are successful are doing it and
um and so let's let's just take the
other end of it
yeah like let's just take let's just
take a concrete example right like a uh
we had this machine learning model at
uber which would estimate how long it
would take your
your uber eats order to be ready for you
right and
and so there's a variety of signals but
let's just talk about two of them uh
that are that could become predictive
features for your machine learning model
one is how long does it normally take
for them to prepare a dish super simple
that you can just calculate once a week
once a month you can calculate it even
once and and just make sure that that's
always available to pass into the model
that's good but sometimes you know
sometimes it's a
a busy time of day or sometimes you know
a restaurant is uncharacteristically
busy like it just got some spike of
of orders and so a second type of signal
which is slightly more complicated
is one that's based on
that's based on some recent
data so it's like you can think of how
many orders did this restaurant get in
the past 30 minutes and how does that
number compare to what they normally get
in a 30-minute period and i can that can
give us a sign of like hey is this like
really really busy right now and if so
then they're probably going to take
longer that's hard to compute in a data
warehouse right data a data warehouse
it may not have all of that real time
you know all the data from the past 30
minutes being available in it and and
there's a it's not meant for kind of
like faster operations like that so at a
company like at like uber what we would
do is we have all of these order events
have uh be populated onto a kafka stream
and then we have
some streaming aggregation jobs
that are
reading these kafka streams aggregating
these data to the number of orders per
restaurant
and a time in an aggregation window
that's like the last 30 minutes always
updated in real time so that when we
need to make a prediction for hey this
restaurant how long is it going to take
to be to have that have that meal
prepared for you
that signal is just is available
immediately for uh for that model to
make that prediction
and
so but your question is like how do
people like practically like if you're
just like a small company or a data
scientist how do you do this
yeah first module
the answer is like realistically you
don't like that's then that's what was
happening at uber when we started is is
just like
a lot of this stuff is is hard and so at
uber and we see this in a lot of other
companies right now they're kind of in
like one of three situations so
situation one as
the it's a super important use case for
the business and like the business needs
this thing to needs this ml model to
work no matter what and so what they do
in those cases is they put a bunch of
engineers on it so the data scientist
comes up with some prototype
and then they hand it off completely to
an engineering team and the engineering
team takes maybe like a notebook of
python code that they may not understand
fully from the data scientists and then
they they productionize it you know
quote unquote productionize it and that
means rewriting some data pipelines in
in a variety of different more
engineering-centric technologies it
means building production services
building the right monitoring a lot of
custom work for a specific it's
basically building like a custom
engineering microservice to make these
predictions
these systems are tend to tend to be
quite brittle very expensive because you
need to staff a whole engineering team
on them and hard to
update right if you're a data scientist
you've got to go through the engineer
every single time so so that's a
challenge with those and when we started
when we started the ml team at uber a
couple years ago
there was there was only a few instances
of teams having gone through that flow
successfully just because it's so
expensive on the engineering side the
second situation is
the data scientist comes up with the
prototype and and then they think okay
this is great like i came up with i
found the model i want to use i brought
together some of the data i wanted to
use and i kind of you know i kind of
simulated what the signals i want to
have for to in that model in my python
environment
now how do i productionize it and then
there's crickets and then nobody knows
how to productionize it there's not a
path to do that like there's basically
there's not the engineers there to
rebuild this whole thing in the
production or the operational
environment and then the and then the
data science project kind of just gets
blocked there and then the data
scientist has other things people are
asking them for and then uh you know
she'll go off and
work on some other projects and that
project will kind of die
the third situation which is very very
common is people don't start on these
projects in the first place data
scientists will know hey i have actually
no path to production there's no way i
can i can build a real-time ml system
that's productionized anyway so i'm just
going to work on this bi other problem
that we have in the company bi problem
i'm going to make some dashboards or
something like that
that's that's very common both from a
data science decision perspective where
they think i don't have a path to
production so why am i going to even
bother
and also from the engineering leadership
perspective where they think wow that
you know if i put my engineers on this
that's so expensive for us from an
engineering cost perspective per ml use
case that i don't even want to support
another ml use case it's just going to
incur more technical debt for us and
it's just going to be more stuff that i
have to support it's not worth it for me
so i think the goal right now for
for the industry is how do we one build
that path to production for data
scientists like make it possible for
them to get their stuff into production
and to lower the cost the engineering
cost so the engineering teams don't see
supporting ml as a burden how do we help
how do we help a given set of engineers
scale to support more and more data
scientists over time
and um just to be clear one of the
things that you mentioned the data
scientist just goes off and builds a
dashboard that is kind of like the
classic analytical machine learning sort
of thing right that's very different
from what you're
what you're trying to say with respect
to actually having models in production
so can you just briefly describe what
that is and then we'll jump into you
know how to solve this whole problem and
this challenge of agility yeah great
question so we started talking about and
this kind of started a couple years ago
but we started
really recognizing that the there's a
big difference in the success and the
cost
of an ml use case depending on who is
the consumer of that use case so when
you think about like hey this is a
machine learning project in my company
it tends to be
that if the machine learning project if
its purpose
is for some internal consumption
something like some analytics purpose or
some let's extract some patterns from
our data so we can you know look at it
and make a decision or let's do a
forecasting of our sales
those tend to be
a lot less costly than the other types
of machine learning projects which we
call operational ml so the first we call
analytic ml second we call operational
ml the operational ml
is use cases that are just in production
they power your product right they're
powering your customer experience these
are things that some of the use cases we
just talked about right like the eta
system at uber or a pricing system that
powers an insurance company's website
right stuff where if it goes down
your product is going to be broken your
business is going to be broken your
customers are going to notice that
requires a different tier of
operationalization a different tier of
productionization and
and when a machine learning project when
a data scientist switches from moving
from analytical machine learning where
kind of they're in control and they are
the end-to-end owners of these systems
and and the stakes frankly are a lot
lower to operational machine learning
projects
where things have slas there's a lot
more uh engineering requirements there's
business there's real business impact if
something doesn't perform
if something's not behaving correctly
that's a real challenge for data
scientists and that's where they begin
really needing
engineering support and so those types
of operational use cases operational ml
is actually like what we focus on at
tecton how do we help people put machine
learning into production and build their
products on the different machine
learning applications that they're
building okay great so now let's talk
about feature stores right so
you mentioned
they're used to operationalize your
machine learning models so can you go
deeper into how that actually solves
this whole problem of operationalizing a
machine learning model great yeah so so
the fundamental like the big cost that
we just talked about about putting a
machine learning an operational machine
learning model into production is that
engineers a lot of engineering resources
are needed
to help a data scientist
rebuild their model in production
rebuild their data pipelines in
production
and so
and so at a high level what a
feature store does is it
resolves that duplication so it provides
a way for a data scientist to define the
data signals the features that they need
in their model and when they define that
at the training stage at the stage when
they're building their model and they're
just exploring
you know what models they want and
they're in that exploration phase
when they define those features those
features are defined in the feature
store and the feature store handles the
productionization of them so an
engineering team is not needed for the
productionization of these features so
what that does is it reduces the need
for data science teams and engineering
teams to collaborate within the core
iteration loop for data science and it
enables data scientists to contribute to
the production model there's no longer
this like throw it over the wall to a
data engineer
the data scientist gets to own their
work they can deploy to production on
their own and they become the owners of
the data science app the whole data
science model all the way through to
production this actually kind of changes
like what their responsibilities are too
right like they're they're no longer the
person who just doesn't really know
exactly what's going on with the
production model they're the owners of
the production model and so the feature
store is the uh management platform and
the platform that runs these pipelines
to in in production so so the workflow
that we enable for a data scientist
is
the ability to define features
declaratively
and then register those features
centrally in the feature store
and then have the feature store
essentially be this kind of this uh
catalog of
trusted signals that are usable by
machine learning applications during the
development and process and production
and so then those features can be can be
used to generate training data sets when
a data scientist is developing to build
models and those features are can also
be queried by
model services prediction services
and from the production environment to
get the latest values of these features
so it's kind of automating a lot of the
data engineering work in productionizing
machine learning applications
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit s-e-radio.net
survey to share a little information
about your professional interests and
listening habits it takes less than two
minutes to help us continue to make sc
radio even better your responses to the
survey are completely confidential
that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
this sounds like uh how databases kind
of change
way back but how you look at your data
and organize and actually query by
having a declarative way to
query and look at your data right so
if i were a data scientist maybe in the
past i had a csv file that i would just
run through
a jupyter notebook or something to look
at the model that works best csv file is
having the data exported from various
different sources so how does a feature
store kind of fit into this where
it's taking you close to the data
directly by bringing that pipeline to
you in some way by saying oh yeah this
is what i care about or this is what i
want how does a feature store solve that
let's do like the juxtaposition of the
before and after right so just for
training a model let's do training
models and then serving models right
like development and productionization
so just for training models
what let's imagine you're making the the
second model in your company so there
actually already is you're making the
second fraud detection model there's
already a fraud detection model in your
company so today what you do is or maybe
like in the past in your example what
you do is connect to various databases
figure out which data you might need
download them to maybe your local
machine
open up those data exports in a python
environment
clean up the data try to join them
together you got to bring all this data
together in one data frame and then run
transformations on this data to
aggregate this data to extract out it's
called you know featurizing and feature
engineering to extract out the relevant
signals for the machine learning
model that you want to build
and train a model and then see if your
model is accurate and then
repeat and one really tough thing here
also is
what you need to do
is
when you're building your training data
set
you have to be very careful about
something that's called data leakage and
in machine learning where you don't want
to have information about the future
leak into your historical data and so a
really hard challenge for data
scientists during this process also is
how do i construct my training data sets
when i have all this exported data
in such a way where yes i'm i'm trans
i'm transforming this data into feature
values with different types of
data transformations but how do i do it
in a way that tells me what that data
what that feature value was at that
point in time and not just what that
feature value is now because the model
needs to be able to train on
on what the model knew would have known
at that time when was making a
prediction in the past so there's a lot
of steps there right now let's talk
about if
for some of our data scientists who are
using feature stores for their model
training phase so
the first thing to know is if this is
your you know your second model in the
company
that means a lot of the features that
are already available that have already
been built in your organization
are already available in a standardized
way for training purposes so
if i'm building a second fraud model i
can go and say hey give me all the user
features this could be hundreds or
thousands of features give me all of the
all of the transaction features and so
maybe i'm already hot starting my
data science project with a thousand
really high quality features which is
which is really nice but i also tend to
for every new use case have to build a
bunch of new features as well and so i i
will be defining some uh pretty
straightforward feature definitions in a
which is basically like like writing
some data transformations into tecton
framework a feature store framework that
that essentially defines a data pipeline
so i'm going to define a data pipeline
and then when i'm trying to extract i'm
trying to generate that training data
set right so i register the data
pipeline into the feature store and now
i want to generate a training data set
what tekton and feature stores generally
should do for the data scientists is
that they handle all of that
historical backfilling of feature values
they handle joining all of the features
the feature values together as of
specific points in time so they really
like protect against a lot of these
really nasty time issues with data that
data scientists always grapple with and
sometimes don't realize
really easy to make some errors here and
generate that training data for the data
scientists so the key points is that it
allows data scientists to reuse a lot of
their work and hot start new efforts and
then also like simplify a lot of the
process of bringing this data together
but the
some of the larger benefits are really
felt at times when
now we're productionizing things because
in the status quo today
you know you go to and the data
scientist goes to their engineer and
says all right cool i found my model
let's productionize this and what did
the what does the engineer say okay so
like what did you build and what should
i what should i build
and you say okay so i have this csv that
i
that i kind of downloaded from a couple
of databases and i wrote this python
script to generate my model so figure it
out you know and the data the data
engineer then has to understand okay how
is that csv created
because that data engineer has to not
just read from that csv but read from
those original data sources so they can
provide
up-to-date data they can always use the
freshest data to uh to have updated
predictions right so they have to
rebuild these data pipelines
and connect to the original data sources
and re-implement all the data
transformations that you had defined in
your in your python notebook
this is this is a painful process and
it obviously sounds painful but
it's like it's the problem is
pretty tricky for larger organizations
where if we talk to some of our kind of
larger enterprise clients they were
having challenges where
these challenges plus governance and
compliance workflows that they deal with
in their large organizations means this
stage can take 6 or 12 months
and
what they really like about the concept
of a feature store is
all of that is just automated for them
actually this problem was solved during
the development time when i defined my
feature and registered my feature into
the feature store back when i was
training a model that productionized
that set up the production data pipeline
automatically so now when it's time to
productionize the model all of the data
pipeline productionization is already
done and the data engineer is not needed
in that loop
so that's a real that's like the real
area for simplification here yeah that
sounds great let's take tecton itself as
an example and uh can you
explain how it connects to various data
sources and then prepares this feature
that a data scientist actually cares
about so tecton has a couple of
components to it there's so at a high
level tecton has a few different
elements it has transformations where it
basically you can think of that as like
the data pipelines that it runs has a
storage layer
and it has uh online survey
and or it has a serving layer and so
each of these elements is configured by
a feature definition so a data scientist
the whole goal is for a data scientist
to be able to self-serve
autonomously define
this is the signal that my model needs
and they should describe that signal i
should just be able to describe that
feature
and
techton
translates that into a configuration for
the data pipelines for the storage and
the data management layer and then for
the online survey so that configures
both the development pipeline and the
production pipeline and so
if you in tecton define say a signal
that is let's just choose one of the
examples we just talked about like how
many orders did this restaurant get and
did a restaurant get in the past 30
minutes right that's a very common type
of type of feature pipeline that someone
would want in their feature store
what technon does is it takes that
definition that you define so you define
a sql query or you may define you may
configure something in our library
through our dsl to specify like a
special type of aggregation but
basically like the definition of the
transformation and then you also write
some of the metadata like
or some specific configuration code that
would say hey i need this available
online this is how i want this signal
backfilled like how far back in time
might i want to train a model using this
signal and a lot of metadata like who's
the owner for this
feature how
trusted is this feature is this an
experimental feature or is this a
production feature
and
register that in tecton what techton
does is it takes that that configuration
and we'll do a couple of things one
it'll turn that it'll orchestrate jobs
compute jobs based on that so it will
for example in this in this streaming
aggregation feature type it will talk to
say a spark your spark cluster and
create a streaming spark job that will
connect to a kafka pipeline
with your events and will
maintain an aggregation maintain these
aggregations it'll run these
aggregations and keep up to date you
know past
number of orders in the past 30 minutes
those values will also be fed into
tecton storage layer which is kind of
like what people think of as the feature
store sometimes and the storage layer is
twofold there's an offline storage layer
which is used to store all of the
historical feature values
for a feature so every time there's a
new version of an updated feature value
it could store it in the offline store
and that's that's used for model
training and model retraining later on
but that data also goes to the online
store which tends to be we plug or
plugable so we plug into different types
of there's different technologies that
can implement our online store but it
tends to be a key value store that's
optimized for fast retrieval and that
will serve that will only hold the
latest values of these signals and then
we have a serving layer
which allows the model the production
model to
query
tecton through a rest api and say hey
i'm fraud model v2 this user is trying
to log in right now
i need all of the signals that the
feature store has that it's prepared and
it maintains fresh for
fraud model v2 what are all the features
for fraud model v2 and i need them
within 50 milliseconds and tecon will
deliver that to the prediction system to
the to the model system which may live
outside of tecton it can be any kind of
model prediction system you have and
then that kind of enables these
real-time predictions so the kind of
value proposition that we deliver to
organizations that are trying to build
these these like complicated real-time
machine learning applications is tekton
is this data platform that simplifies
all of the data pipelines needed to be
built and deployed for uh real-time ml
and it really kind of simplifies the
development and productionization
workflows there so a data scientist
can not only just like build a prototype
but they can run a model in production
on their own as well gotcha so let's say
you have multiple data scientists right
now who are publishing these features in
uh in tecton how do they go around
discovering that someone else has
actually prepared this feature for me or
i can actually work off of someone
else's pipeline and feature that they've
already built for my model because i
think this is useful yeah that's a
really good question and it's a pretty
important capability of the feature
store to eliminate duplication so
there's
there's a couple of reasons why you
might want to do this there's obviously
like the cost component where you just
don't want two signals that you don't
want the same compute these pipelines
can be pretty expensive right they're
heavyweight data processing jobs often
you just don't want these same things to
be running again and again for no reason
but secondly
it can be confusing to people if
two signals are implemented like i said
or rather one signal is implemented
twice but slightly differently and they
have different implementations and then
that can lead to people not recognizing
that they're actually implemented
differently and not being careful about
which one they're using and you may
train a model in one
using one signal but then you if you're
trying to make a prediction with like
another implementation of that same
signal if it's slightly off your model
could misbehave and that may be hard to
predict but that will lead to model
performance issues so i'm bringing that
up because
there's a lot of reasons why
transparency is really important
discoverability is really important for
these signals for machine learning and
so what the feature store does is
provides a catalog of these production
ready signals so this is largely a
knowledge management issue but it's like
i'm a data scientist how do i find which
features are already productionized that
i can use today
literally a search interface in a web ui
i can see a catalog i can browse search
by user search by feature type search by
entity so i can say what are all the
user features what are all the
item features what are all the you know
an uber we had what are the driver
features and the writer features stuff
like that
and i can also see all of a variety of
pieces of metadata so hey this is an
experimental feature you may not want to
build your model based on this
or this is a solid production feature
that 10 other models depend on so you're
going to be fine if you depend your
model on that
that kind of like visibility as and
discoverability is critical for
allowing machine learning to scale in a
company because once you have that then
you can kind of enable the reuse and
sharing that we were talking about
before
so now when i have my second machine
learning model
i don't have to start from zero i can go
to the feature store and say hey what
are the list of features that are kind
of relevant for me that i might want to
try out
instead of me rebuilding a thousand
signals let me just reuse the top 1000
signals that my company has already put
together and maybe that's all i need to
do and maybe i can finish this machine
learning project in one day instead of a
couple of months so this is where that
value of having
your machine learning idea going from
a year to actually get data engineers to
put the pipelines can go into you know
two or three days into production and
that's really nice one thing you
mentioned was the storage aspect of it
and is that can you elaborate on what
the storage looks like you know you said
there's batch there's real time so
is it going back to the source systems
or is the separate database or something
can you talk about that yeah good point
so the way this is implemented is
so we need there's two types of storage
in a feature store there's an offline
storage layer which holds the historical
values and the online storage layer
which is well it's the latest values but
it's optimized for fast retrieval
and so what typed on so so techdon is a
cloud native solution that reuses a lot
of
the cloud managed services but it's
built in a very plugable way so tecton
doesn't have a proprietary you know
offline storage layer or a proprietary
online key value store or anything like
that what we do is we plug into your
infrastructure so if you
use snowflake if you use a data
warehouse we will store we will use that
data warehouse as the offline storage
layer so we'll all of the feature tables
all the feature data will just look like
normal tables in your snowflake or your
redshift for example and if you have a
redis cluster that you want to use for
that you already are using your
applications already connecting to for
online serving
we'll use that as the online storage
layer or we come out of the box with
with uh we will configure like a dynamo
and we'll use dynamo on aws to serve
this stuff so you can think of the
feature store as like a coordinating
layer that brings together a lot of
pieces of infrastructure that is already
available on the cloud or in your in
your account to allow you to
allow your data scientists to configure
these data flows that become coherent
production data pipelines for machine
learning applications and coordinate all
these different pieces of infrastructure
to enable that
does that make sense yeah that makes a
lot of sense yeah i think that is where
a lot of the complexity would be with uh
data engineer trying to deliver this
model to predict to production would be
can i actually have a real-time key
value store or something that gives me
online data how do i configure that how
do i maintain that what are the needs so
i can i can see the simplification with
say having a feature store being able to
plug into your infrastructure and then
serve that and that's great so let's
talk about quality aspects of it right
so you train your model and then you
know you want to generate v2 of your
model how do you monitor how your v1 is
doing and how do you transition that
into say i'm going to actually do v2
because you know v1 is deteriorating in
terms of what it's serving yeah i think
i so i think there's a couple of
questions there the
important thing that everyone who's
running machine learning operationally
like running machine learning in a way
that it has real business impact
i think that's very important to do is
measure the performance of your model
and that is that can be harder or easier
depending on the use case so in a
situation here's an example of how it's
really easy i'm going to predict if
you're going to i'm in a recommendation
system i'm going to predict if you're
going to click on this recommendation
and immediately after you know in five
seconds from now i'm gonna know if you
clicked it or you didn't click it it's
very easy for me to and then say
calculate my accuracy right
and but if i'm predicting fraud for
example you know maybe i only find out
that this was a purchase made with a
stolen credit card 90 days later when a
credit card company comes back to me and
does a chargeback or something like that
so that's a whole other data engineering
challenge to like how do we associate
that data we collect 90 days from now
back with this prediction log that we
made you know from from the past
there's not just my point is there's not
just like one way to
measure accuracy in
a super simple way but once you can
bring that data together then there's a
couple of things that you want to do you
want to have a good sense of what the
steady state performance is and track
the performance of that model but you
also want to have a good sense of like
how i could improve this model and so
you ask like hey how do i know when to
retrain it
there's there's a couple of
you know there's two kinds of questions
there it's like how do i know when my
system stops operating correctly and how
do i know when i have an opportunity to
an opportunity to improve this system
and i think practically right now
the opportunity to improve this system
is driven by intuition by people so
it's hey we have hey we just realized we
have this data source in the company
that we're not using in this model but
it's kind of like it kind of makes sense
that it could help us make better
recommendations so maybe we want to test
it out
and let's run a let's build a prototype
where we join in that kind of data and
train a model on that kind of data
and you know sometimes in a lot of use
cases you can only really test these
things out when you put them in
production
so that's that's kind of like how do we
know how to improve the system when
we're thinking about how to
how to detect issues that's where you
have to monitor that accuracy signal
over time and if that accuracy signal
decreases in some way that might mean
you need to retrain your model or that
might mean there's a challenge there's a
breakage somewhere in one of your data
pipelines or a data quality issue
so when you say you want to retrain your
model you also mentioned sometime in the
past that you store historical data
in offline storage is that offline
storage used predominantly for
retraining or is it also just because
you can have batch jobs on it to serve
your model the offline storage is used
mainly for model training so it can be
for training new models or for
retraining a model right you know the
feature store doesn't care it's just
generating a training data set but
that's why we have this historical these
historical values in the offline store
because it allows the feature store to
easily create a training data set that
says
for each time someone logged in in the
past for example if that's what we're
predicting if that's the granularity of
our predictions what was the features
value at that point in time in the past
and that allows you to generate easily
generate a training data set that
doesn't have any label leakage it
doesn't have any any bad feature leakage
and so so you can easily create high
quality training data sets without a lot
of the data science complexity that
usually comes along with that
yeah that's great so the feature store
concept itself is fairly new right so
there's a couple of players in the field
uh techton is one and i think amazon has
like sagemaker databricks has one what
is like the common
common components of a future store that
you see in that everyone agrees on i'm
sure everyone has their own value
proposition but what makes a feature
store a feature store that everyone
agrees on yeah so the
core
thing that everyone agrees on is that
there's an online and offline serving
layer and so you know this is a new
category it's a new actually most things
in the machine learning like the ml ops
world in the mlab stack
it's very fresh and so a lot of
different teams are figuring out exactly
what is the scope what are the
boundaries of a specific product
we've developed the feature we kind of
developed our feature store in uh uber
and we coined the term feature storm
we've been working on feature source for
a long time so we're pretty confident
about the
about like tecton's kind of geometry but
if you look across every
every product that uses the term feature
store what they have in common is they
have a way to retrieve features quickly
and at low latency for on online
prediction and they have ways to get
historical data from from an offline
storage layer and that's kind of the
crux of the feature store is managing
that kind of data duplication across
these different types of data
infrastructure so a feature store kind
of like connects various systems across
your company right so your model might
be really critical for your business you
might have an sla that says you know we
never want this model to be down but it
also has dependencies on upstream
systems like maybe there's a database
that does not have the same guarantees
that it's going to be up all time uh
maybe it's going to be down every sunday
for a batch or an upgrade or something
so how do you tie in the availability of
your models with
upstream systems that actually have the
data somewhere yeah so that's part of
the feature store's goal is to
hide to provide an abstraction for the
data scientist to hide that complexity
of the upstream data infrastructure so
when a feature is
defined in a feature store that's when
you address some of that complexity and
you say
you know what how often should this
feature be recomputed and where is this
feature coming from and some of the
other details about how you can access
this feature depending on the context
but then after that feature is
registered in the feature store
it should look like to the person who's
using the feature store just like any
other feature so it doesn't matter if
this is a real-time computer feature a
streaming feature or a batch feature
they're all just they're all just
productionized features available within
this common machine learning focused
catalog
that i can use to build an offline data
set or i can depend a production model
on and so that kind of standardization
or that the
that abstraction
enables that kind of standardized
consumption of these data and that's
that's a lot that hides a lot of the
complexity and makes and speeds up the
data scientists in a pretty significant
way
let's talk a little bit about the
compliance aspects and data governance
aspects of it a lot of companies
especially large ones they have huge
implications if you don't actually
follow some of the data governance
standards maybe
a user comes back and says hey under
gdpr or california privacy loss you know
i want this data to be deleted about me
how does that flow into
through this entire pipeline of systems
that you have where
it may impact the predictions that you
can do it may impact you know my
experience how does how does this tie in
together yeah there's two approaches
right one approach is to build specific
capabilities for every
single
type of regulation
and you know what that means practically
is build specific capabilities for like
very common prominent pieces of
regulation and the second is
to
make knowledge management much easier
here and
the that second approach is is the
is the thing that is the easier one to
take on and that's where we are and
basically frankly where most of the
feature store industry is right now is
about tracking metadata so it's like
we give you the capability to tag
different data resources with hey this
contains pii this is sensitive data this
is how this data should be treated this
is the policy that is associated with
this upstream data set and the feature
store ensures that downstream data sets
are similarly tagged according to those
policies and it'll and it leaves it up
to
the
the consumer or the data team to make
sure that those data are being handled
appropriately right it's not it's not
like uh the actions are not being taken
within the feature store but at least
the knowledge is being uh conveyed
accurately
but but there's more that a feature
store can do
like for example providing a gdpr
deletion api so
there's a variety of gdpr deletion
requests
can the data scientists build a way to
automatically this is part of like the
maintenance of a data pipeline for ml
automatically handle the gdpr requests
for their ml pipelines as well and what
does that mean
okay user x needs to be deleted well we
need to wipe them from all historical
training data we need to wipe them their
features from the online feature store
we just got to basically purge them from
the system and that introduces a lot of
yet unsolved machine learning challenges
because
if i train my model on this data set
and now we've deleted an item from there
can my model be retrained now
right and what is the implication on my
model if it cannot be exactly retrained
because we're not allowed to have that
data anymore
how do i when i'll go to retrain my
model how do i generate that training
data set
a lot of these questions are handled on
an ad hoc basis right now and we're
working with our customers to build in
the right kind of patterns out of the
box to solve this stuff for them
that's uh that's great to hear i wanted
to start wrapping up can you talk about
you know what's in the future for
feature stores this is such a new thing
right now uh so i'm sure there's going
to be a lot of change what do you think
is going to be the future of feature
stores yeah i think the future for
feature stores the immediate future is
to continue growing frankly we have a
lot of people are just learning about
feature stores today but feature stores
are
have been in use for years at some of
the top ml companies in the world you
know
all of the top tech companies that you
can imagine and so what's next for
for us and for feature stores generally
is to to just education just making sure
people understand what future stores are
and making it as simple as possible for
people to adopt some really cool things
that
our customers have asked us for that are
likely coming next some some interesting
things are for example one how do i
automatically create great features from
my data can we can we like auto
featurize upstream data
secondly is can we have
uh can i have features in my models that
do not come from my data but come from
someone else's data so maybe there can
be some third-party features that
provide some context like like you know
some really important things for the
uber eats models that we were talking
about before is like what's the weather
and what is the traffic outside maybe
that would be really great for me to use
those features and my model out of the
box right and that's something that kind
of like a notion of a future marketplace
could be really useful in uh in a
feature store what's next for us is just
keeping keep on working with our
different customers still a lot to build
there's a lot to
to do to support additional use cases
there's a huge variety of requirements
in the in across ml use cases but then
there's some of these like really
interesting kind of like next generation
things that can expand the value
propositions of feature stores i just
mentioned a few of them but some other
announcements will be coming out soon
well it's been great talking to you mike
thank you for coming on the show
actually thank you so much this is
akshay munchali for software engineering
radio thank you for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening